Vercors' famous novel
The Silence of the Sea
In memory of the murdered poet,
Saint-Pol-Roux
This film does not claim to provide
a solution to the relations...
... between France and Germany,
which will remain problematic...
...while the barbaric Nazi crimes...
...carried out with the collusion
of the German people stay in our minds
He had left like that
He submitted to life like all the others
Like the whole wretched nation
And I tried to remember everything
that had happened in these six months
The evenings, his words...
...the rebellion that even this man
did not have the courage to continue...
...against his master's orders
His arrival was preceded by a great deal
of military preparation
Later the gangling soldier came back
accompanied by another
They spoke to me
in what they thought was French
I didn't understand a word
But I showed them
the unoccupied rooms
They seemed satisfied
The next morning...
...an army car
made its way into the garden
Two soldiers extricated two boxes
The car left and a few hours later
I heard horses
Three men on horseback appeared
They had pushed my workbench clamp
between stones in the wall...
...attached a rope to it and the horses
to the rope by the barn, my workshop
Nothing happened for the next two days
I didn't see anyone
The men left early with their horses
They returned with them in the evening,
sleeping on the straw they had put down
Then on the morning of the third day,
the army car returned
A pair of sheets, please
My niece had just brought me my coffee
as she did every evening
Coffee helps me to sleep
I was sitting at the end of the room,
more or less in the dark
If you please
My name is Werner von Ebrennac
I'm very sorry, l...
It was necessary, of course.
I would have avoided it, if I'd been able
My orderly will do everything he can
not to disrupt you
I have a deep respect
for people who love their country
I could go to my room now,
but I don't know the way
My niece opened the door leading
onto the stairs and started to climb...
...without looking at the officer
as if she was alone
The officer followed her
I noticed that he had a limp
My niece came back down
Thank God, he seems quite decent
Next morning the officer came down
as we were breakfasting in the kitchen
A different staircase leads down to it
I don't know if he'd heard us
or if he just happened to come this way
He said
I had a very good night
I hope yours was as good
Your old mayor said
I'd be staying at the Ch?teau
But I'll thank my men for getting it wrong.
It's much more beautiful here
He returned at the same time as before.
We were having coffee
He knocked but didn't wait for my niece
and opened the door himself
I fear I'm disturbing you
If you prefer,
I'll come in via the kitchen?
Then you can lock this door
I bid you good night
We never locked the door
I'm not sure this was for a very clear
or blameless reason
My niece and I had silently agreed
not to change our lives at all...
... not even the slightest detail
As if the officer didn't exist.
As if he were a ghost
But in my heart
there may have been another reason
It pains me to offend anyone,
even if he is my enemy
For a long time, more than a month,
the same scenario was played out
The officer would knock and enter
He would say something about
the weather, the temperature
or some such subject of little importance
Their common trait -
none of them required a response
He always lingered at the hearth.
He looked around him
A faint smile betrayed the pleasure
he took in this exercise
Always the same exercise,
always the same pleasure
His eyes rested
on my niece's bowed profile...
...which was always severe
and impassive
When he finally took his eyes off her...
... I saw in them
a kind of smiling approval
I bid you good night
Things suddenly changed one evening
A light snow was falling, mixed with rain,
it would both freeze and drench you
I put the thickest logs on the fire
that had been set aside for such days
I imagined the officer outside covered in
a sprinkling of snow on his return
But he didn't return
It was long past his usual time...
...and to my annoyance
I found myself thinking about him
My niece was knitting slowly
and with great concentration
Finally we heard footsteps...
... but they came from inside the house
From the uneven sound
I could tell it was the officer
He'd come in by the other door
and was now leaving his room
He no doubt hadn't wanted to appear
inglorious in his drenched uniform
He had first changed
The footsteps, one loud, one quiet,
came down the stairs
The door opened
and the officer appeared
He was in mufti
Excuse me, I'm not very warm.
I got drenched and my room is very cold
I'll warm myself by your fire
for a moment
That's good
This is nothing.
The French winter is mild
It's hard where I'm from, very hard
We have fir trees,
the forests are tightly packed
The snow sits heavy on them
The trees here are delicate
the snow covers them like lace
Germany is like a powerful thickset bull...
...which needs all its strength to stay alive
Here, it's all intellect, thought,
subtle and poetic
I've always loved France. Always
My childhood thoughts
in the last war mean nothing
But I've always loved it since
But it was from a distance.
Like the "Faraway Princess"
Because of my father
He was very patriotic
The defeat was very painful for him
But he loved France
He liked Briand. He believed
in the Weimar Republic and in Briand
He was very enthusiastic
He would say,
" He'll unite us like man and wife"
He thought the sun
would finally rise over Europe
But Briand was defeated
My father saw that France
was still run by your cruel upper classes
Men like de Wendels, Henri Bordeaux
and the old Marshal
He said to me, never go to France...
... unless it is in a soldier's garb
I made him that promise
because he was dying
When war broke out,
I knew all of Europe, except France
I'm a musician.
I'm not a performer, I compose music
It's my whole life
So it's strange for me to see myself
as a fighting man
But I don't...
I don't regret this war
No, I think
some great good will come of it
Forgive me if I have offended you
but I sincerely believe what I said
Out of love for France
Great things will come of it
for both Germany and France
I think as my father did
that the sun will shine again on Europe
I bid you good night
Perhaps it's inhumane
to refuse to speak to him
I almost felt myself blush
From that day on
this was the pattern his visits took
We rarely saw him in his uniform...
... he changed first,
then knocked at our door
Whether to spare us the enemy uniform...
...to make us forget
or to get to know the man?
Both, no doubt
He knocked and entered, not waiting
for the reply he knew we wouldn't give
He did it in the most natural way
and warmed himself
This was always his excuse,
but neither he nor we believed it...
...and he did not try to disguise
its conventionality
He didn't come every single evening
but I don't remember one...
...when he did not talk
He leaned over the fire,
and while he warmed himself...
... his deep voice would gently rise...
...and he would talk about the things
close to his heart...
... his country, music, France
It was always a monologue...
...as he never tried to pries from us
a response, an agreement...
...or even a look
He wouldn't speak for long,
never longer than on the first evening
He would say a few sentences,
sometimes broken by silence...
...sometimes linked up with the
monotonous continuity of a prayer
He would sometimes stand motionless,
a caryatid against the chimney breast...
...or without breaking off,
go up to an object or a picture
Then he would fall silent,
bow and bid us goodnight
Once, in the early days of his visits,
he said...
How is this different from
a fire at home?
The wood, the hearth, the flame
are the same, but the light is different
This one depends on the objects it lights,
the people in this room
Why do I like this room so much?
It's not so beautiful.
Oh, I'm sorry, I mean...
It's not a museum piece.
Your furniture, not beautiful artifacts...
No, but this room has a soul
The whole house has a soul
Balzac, Baudelaire, Corneille, Descartes,
Fenelon, Gautier, Hugo
What a line-up!. And I've only got to 'H'
Not as far as Moliere, Racine, Rabelais.
Pascal, Stendhal, Voltaire, Montaigne...
...and all the others
With the English,
you immediately think of Shakespeare
With the Italians, Dante
With Spain, Cervantes...
...and with us, immediately Goethe
Then you have to stop and think...
... but if someone says France,
who immediately springs to mind?
Moliere? Racine? Hugo?
Voltaire? Rabelais?
Or who of the others?
They're like a crowd at a theatre entrance.
You don't know who to let in first
But in terms of music, you think of us
Bach, H?ndel,
Beethoven, Wagner, Mozart
Which name do you put first?
And we are at war with each other!.
But it is the last. We won't fight any more,
we will marry
Yes
It will be the most beautiful wedding
in the world
I bid you good night
My dear, I'm going back to warm up
But he never mentioned this meeting
When we entered Saintes,
I was happy that we got a good reception
I was very happy.
I thought it would be easy
Then I saw that it was not
that at all, it was cowardice
I felt contempt for them
and I feared for France
I thought, " Has it really come to this?"
No, I've since seen it's not so...
...and now I'm happy to see
its stern expression
I'm happy to have found here
a dignified old man...
...and a silent young lady
We have to overcome this silence,
we have to overcome France's silence
I'm glad it's so
Then one evening...
Yes, it's better like this, much better.
It makes for a better union
A union in which each side
grows in greatness
There's a lovely fairytale that I've read,
that you've read, that everyone has read
I don't know if the title is the same
We call it ¡°Das Tier und die Sch?ne¡±...
¡°Beauty and the Beast¡±
Poor Beauty. She is at the mercy
of the Beast, his powerless prisoner
She is subjected to his impassive
and heavy presence all day long
Beauty is proud, dignified,
she has become hard
But the Beast is better than it seems
It doesn't have the finest manners
It is gauche, brutal
It seems uncouth
next to the refined Beauty
But it has a heart.
Yes, a soul which aspires to greater things
If Beauty wanted
Beauty takes a long time to do so
But gradually she discovers a light
in her hated captor's eyes...
...a light where entreaty
and love are discernible
She becomes less aware
of its heavy paw, her prison chains
She stops hating it. Its constancy
touches her and she gives it her hand
The Beast is immediately transformed
The spell that had trapped him
in this barbaric pelt is broken
He is a handsome knight with a pure heart,
sensitive and cultured...
...and every kiss from Beauty adorns him
with ever more glorious qualities
Their union leads
to their sublime happiness
Their children who combine
their parents' talents...
...are the most beautiful on earth
Don't you like this fairytale?
I've always loved it
I'm always reading it
It used to make me cry
I especially like the Beast
because I understood his suffering
It still moves me today
when I talk about it
I bid you good night
One evening when I went up to my room
to get some tobacco...
... I heard the strains of the harmonium
The Eighth Prelude and Fugue my niece
had been practising before the disaster
The score stayed open at that page...
... but until then
my niece had not practised again
I was pleased and surprised
she had gone back to it
What emotional need could have suddenly
made her take it up again?
No, she had not left her chair or her work
There's nothing greater
Great is not quite the right word
Beyond man, beyond his flesh
It makes us realise... no... guess... no...
...sense what nature is...
...divine nature,
divested of the human mind
Yes, it's inhuman music
Bach. He could only be German
Our land has this inhuman characteristic
By 'inhuman' I mean
it's not on the same scale as men
I love this music, I admire it
It overwhelms me
It is like God's presence in me
But it's not my music
I want to compose music
on a human scale
It's a way of arriving at the truth.
My way
I don't want another,
I can't follow any other
I know that now. I know it for sure
Since when?
Since I've been here
Now I need France, but I ask a lot of her.
I ask her to welcome me
It doesn't mean anything to be here
as a foreigner, a traveller, a conqueror
She doesn't give anything
because you can't take anything from her
Her wealth, her great wealth
will not be conquered
You have to drink her milk
She has to offer you her milk
like a mother
I know that depends on us
but it depends on her, too
She has to be willing
to understand our thirst...
...and to quench it
She has to be ready to join with us
I need to live here for a long time,
in a house like this
Like the son of a village, a village like this
I need...
Obstacles have to be overcome
Sincerity can always overcome obstacles
I bid you good night
I don't remember all that was said
over a hundred winter evenings
But it was always the same
Always his rapture
about his discovery of France
The love he had felt from afar
before coming here
The love which grew each day
since he had the good fortune to live here
And I have to say I admired him
He never got discouraged, never tried
to break our intractable silence...
... by any verbal outbursts
On the contrary, when he sometimes
let the silence take over the room...
...and seep into its corners
like a heavy unbreathable gas...
...of the three of us,
he seemed to be most at ease
He looked approvingly at my niece...
... his expression
both smiling and solemn...
...as it had been from the first day
And I felt my niece's soul struggle
in her self-imposed prison
I saw it in the little signs,
like the slight trembling of her fingers
When Werner von Ebrennac finally
gently and smoothly broke this silence...
...with his deep voice
I felt able to breathe more easily
I was born in my house in the forest.
I went to the village school
I didn't leave it until I went to Munich for my
exams and to Salzburg for the music
I've always lived there.
I didn't like the cities
I've been to London, Vienna,
Rome, Warsaw...
...and of course to German cities
I wouldn't like to live there
I did like Prague.
It has a soul like no other
And Nuremberg above all else
It's the city that fills a German's heart...
... because you find ghosts
which are close to your heart...
...every stone imbued with the memory
of those who made Germany noble
I imagine the French must feel the same
at Chartres
They must also feel the presence
of their ancestors...
...their graciousness of spirit,
the splendour of their faith, their kindness
Fate took me to Chartres
Attention!
350 metres. Prepare
Fire!
It's so. So many things are going on
in a German's head
Even in the best German,
and he'd be glad to be cured of them
In the country house near us
lives a young woman
She is very beautiful and very sweet
My father would have been happy
if I had married her
We were practically engaged
when he died...
...and we went for long walks on our own
One day we were in the forest and...
I'm so happy, Werner
- All God's creations are so wonderful.
- Yes, I'm happy too
Wretched creature! It stung me
Look, I've caught it, Werner
Now I'm going to punish it
I'll tear off its legs, one by one
Fortunately she had a lot of other suitors
I have no regrets
But I'm terrified of German girls now
Our politicians are like that too
I never wanted anything to do with them
Even though my friends wrote saying,
"Come and join us"
No
I always preferred to stay at home
It wasn't the best thing for the success
of my music, but too bad
Success counts for little
compared to a clear conscience
I know that my friends and the Fuhrer
have the greatest and most noble ideas
But I also know that they would tear off
mosquitoes' legs, one by one
That always happens to Germans
when they are lonely
It always comes back
Who is lonelier than the men in the Party
when they rule?
Fortunately they're not alone now.
They are in France
France will cure them
And they know it
They know France will teach them
to be truly great and pure-hearted
But for that, they need love
A shared love
I bid you good night
The long spring days arrived
The officer now returned
with the last of the sun's rays
The Fuhrer announces far-reaching
historic decisions will be made
One evening he came down,
a book closed over his finger
He wore the suppressed half smile
of one who knows...
... he is about to make others happy...
He said
I'm sorry to disturb you so early
but I have this for you
It's from 'Macbeth'
Such greatness
It's at the end
Macbeth's power is slipping away
and with it the loyalty of those...
...who finally realise
the depths of his ambition
The noblemen who defend Scotland's
honour waiting for his imminent downfall
One of them describes
the dramatic symptoms of this downfall
Angus: now does he feel
his secret murders sticking on his hands
He is upbraided by a revolt each minute
for his breach of faith
Those he commands
move only in command
Nothing in love
Now does he feel his title
hang loose about him...
... Iike a giant's robe
upon a dwarfish thief
That's what must give your president
some sleepless nights
I pity this man, despite the contempt
he inspires in me and in you
Those he commands
move only in command, nothing in love
A leader who does not have the love
of his people is a miserable puppet
But can we hope for anything else?
Who but a dreary climber
would have taken on this role?
There needed to be someone
who would sell his country...
... because today France
cannot willingly fall into our open arms...
...without losing her dignity
in her own eyes
Often the most sordid go-between
is responsible for the happiest union
The go-between is no less contemptible
for it, nor the union less happy
The Paris train
I must inform my hosts
I shall be away for two weeks
I'm delighted about going to Paris
I have my leave and I'm going to spend it
in Paris, for the first time
It's a big day for me
The biggest, while I wait for another
which I hope for with all my soul
It will be an even bigger day
I can wait. For years, if need be
My heart is very patient
In Paris I'll see my friends
Many are party to the negotiations
being conducted with your politicians...
... in preparation for the wonderful union
of our two nations
In a way I'll witness this marriage
I want to tell you that I'm happy for France
whose wounds will quickly heal
But I'm even happier for Germany
and for myself
No one will ever have benefited more
from a good deed than Germany will...
... by restoring France's greatness
and freedom
I bid you good night
The French army
threatened to invade England
The Third Coalition took up arms
on the continent
Napoleon entered Vienna,
he triumphed at Austerlitz
In less than 100 days
the Coalition was dissolved
I was sent here by God, King of Heaven,
to drive you out of France
We didn't see him when he returned
We knew he was there, there are
many signs of a guest in the house...
...even if he remains invisible
But for a number of days,
more than a week, we didn't see him
Should I admit to it?
This absence troubled me
I thought about him
I think I felt regret and concern
Neither my niece nor I spoke of it
But when in the evening,
we heard his uneven tread...
... I saw from the way she suddenly and
stubbornly applied herself to her work...
...and from the faint lines
on her face...
...giving her an expression that was
both determined and expectant...
...that her thoughts were similar to mine
I had to go to the German headquarters
to make some declaration about tyres
Come in
For a free Europe
What do you want?
Lieutenant
- Make five copies and send them one.
- Yes, Lieutenant
I didn't say anything about it to my niece,
but women have a feline intuition
All evening she kept looking up
from her work...
...and looking at me
trying to discern something in my face...
...which I forced into an expressionless
blank by diligently drawing on my pipe
She finally dropped her hands
as if she was tired...
...and folding the material asked for
my permission to go to bed early
She kissed me and I think I saw
in her beautiful grey eyes...
...a reproach and a heavy sadness
Once she had left
I felt an absurd anger rise in me
Anger at being absurd
and having an absurd niece
What was this stupidity?
I couldn't answer that
If it was stupidity
it seemed to be deeply ingrained
Three days later,
just as we were finishing our coffee...
...we heard the familiar footsteps
with their irregular tread...
...coming in our direction
I suddenly remembered that winter evening
when we had first heard his footsteps...
...six months earlier
I thought, it's raining today too
My niece had put a square of printed silk
around her shoulders
I was warming my hands on the bowl
of my pipe and it was summer!
I thought I could see a man
behind the door...
... his forefinger raised, ready to knock...
...and delaying the moment...
...for by the very act of knocking,
he would set in motion the future
Finally he knocked
Not with the lightness of one hesitating
nor the brusqueness of shyness overcome
They were three full and long knocks
Calm, assured knocks of a decision
on which there was no going back
I was expecting to see the door open
immediately as usual
But it remained shut and I was overcome
by an uncontrollable uneasiness
He's going to leave
What should I do to behave with dignity
on this evening?
Come in, sir
I learned then that the hands,
if you observe them well...
...can be as expressive as the face
Even better than the face...
...as they more easily escape
the control of the will
I have something serious to tell you
Everything I have said
these past six months
Everything the walls of this room
have heard...
...you have to...
...you have to forget
Such a light!
I saw these victorious men
I spoke to them
They laughed at me
I had been so happy to go there
Treblinka?
- Yes, what about it?
- What's the significance of Treblinka?
- Nothing, nothing now.
- Why "not any more"?
Let's not talk about that.
It's not for the faint-hearted
The mass executions take place
in the gas chambers constructed here...
... with carbon monoxide
and in the cremation ovens
There is currently
a throughput of 500 people a day...
... but improvements are underway...
... so that within two months...
... this figure can be increased
to 2,000 people a day
Treblinka. 21 March. 1941
The start of spring!
So these gas chambers
are currently in use
No, Treblinka has already
served its purpose. It's done with
There's no one left to execute
Chemical examination post
Medical centre
I'm surprised by your opinion on this
Haven't you realised
that we're duping them?
Do you think we're foolish enough
to let France rise up again?
We're not musicians
Politics isn't the stuff of fantasy.
Why do you think we went to war?
- For the sake of their old Marshal?
- We're not mad
We have the opportunity to destroy
France and that's what we will do
Not just its power, but its spirit as well
That's where the greatest danger lies.
That's our duty
Make no mistake,
we'll do it with smiles and with care...
... but we'll make France crawl on its belly
You've been too influenced by France
in your youth, that's the danger...
... but we'll cure Europe of this disease,
we'll root out this poison
We'll flatter the writers of course...
... but we've already taken
the necessary measures
In Belgium and Holland
and in every country we occupy
French books will be allowed
except technical publications
There will be no literary works.
None!
We'll rip the venom from the beast
Getting frightened
Now they fear for their pockets,
their stomachs, their industry and trade
That's all they're worried about
There are exceptions, of course,
but we'll flatter them to death
- Nothing could be easier.
- Just for a plate of lentils
Do you realise what you're doing?
- Do you realise?
- Do you think we'll falter?
We're made of stronger stuff
You will seal France's downfall
forever
It's a matter of life and death
Violence can conquer but it cannot rule
We know that.
It takes more than an army to rule
Not at the price of the spirit
Not at that price
The spirit? It has already seen a lot
The spirit is immortal.
We're building a thousand year Reich
First we have to destroy
That's our right and our duty
On September 19, 1941
another German soldier was murdered
To atone for this cowardly crime
the following were shot
Wait a moment
A box of matches, please
There is no hope
No hope
Nothing
No one
Not just the modern authors.
Not just Peguy, Proust, Bergson
But all the others, all of these.
All of them
They will extinguish the light
Completely
That light will never shine again on Europe
One of these men was my friend
He was like a brother
We studied together.
We shared a room in Stuttgart
We spent three months together
in Nuremberg
I played him my music
He read me his poems
He was sensitive and romantic
But he left me
He went to read his poems in Munchen,
in Munich
To new friends
He was always writing
asking me to join him
It was he I saw in Paris with his friends
I saw what they had done to him
He was the angriest of them all
He combined anger and laughter
He shouted " It's venomous, we have
to extract the venom from the beast"
I said,
"Do you realise what you're doing?"
I looked at him,
I looked into his bright eyes
He meant what he said,
that's the worst part
They will do what they say...
... methodically and resolutely
I know these stubborn devils
His lips opened and I thought he was
going to launch into some exhortation
I thought he was going to encourage us
to rebel
But no word passed his lips
They said to me,
"It's our right and our duty"
"Our duty"
Lucky the man
who so easily finds the path to his duty
At the crossroads, you're told,
take that route
This route does not take you
towards the shining heights...
... it descends into a gloomy valley...
...deep into the dark, dank forest
Oh God, show me where my duty lies
Can duty ever mean accepting the crime?
I've exercised my rights.
I've asked to join a fighting division
They've finally agreed to it
I'm authorised to leave tomorrow
and return to battle
Towards Hell
I bid you good night
Goodbye
You'd have to have been waiting
to have heard this word
But finally I heard it.
Von Ebrennac heard it, too
Take my things downstairs
It is a fine thing when a soldier disobeys
criminal orders
All set, Lieutenant
Yes, I'm coming
My niece had made me breakfast
as usual
She served me in silence
We drank our coffee in silence
Outside a pale sun was shining
through the mist
It felt very cold to me
October 1941
The publication of this book
was funded by a patriot
The printing was completed under
Nazi Occupation on 20 February 1942